Finding Aid for Wilbert J. McKeachie Papers 1941-1991
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Psychology
  - Speeches
    - Miscellaneous
      - The Structures of Learning and Structures of the University, 1975 (Box 4)
      - The Utopian University, undated (Box 4)
        (probably 1991-1992)
  - Topical
    The Topical series (1.5 linear feet) is arranged alphabetically. The Biographical materials include vitae (the 1986 version includes a chronology of McKeachie's service on various university committees), a draft of a chapter written by McKeachie for T. S. Krawiec's The Psychologists (available at the University of Michigan Harlan Hatcher Graduate Library), which is an informative and enlightening autobiographical sketch, and the transcript of a lengthy interview with a former student. There are files from McKeachie's work as a member of external review committees evaluating psychology departments and various programs at other colleges and universities around the country. The University of Michigan files document only in part McKeachie's service on various committees and boards. There are interesting reports and correspondence in his Athletics files; other committee files also contain reports and correspondence, some minutes, and collected materials. There is particularly interesting correspondence in the Department of Psychology files in which he reflects on the state of teaching, research, and administration in the department, and his views on the importance of doctoral training in educational or instructional psychology for graduate students in education are reflected in the file on Education and Psychology. The Faculty Senate file includes speeches given on various topics by McKeachie in his role as chairman of the Senate Advisory Committee on University Affairs.
    - Biographical, 1946-1992; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1977 (Box 4)
      (regarding Arthur Jensen as fellow)
    - American Association of University Professors (AAUP)
      - General, 1972-1989 (Box 4)
      - Committee C, 1971-1980; 3 folders (Box 4)
    - American Council on Education, 1961-1979 (Box 4)
    - American Institute for Research in the Behavioral Sciences (AIR)
      - General, 1978-1987 (Box 4)
      - President Search, 1987; 2 folders
        - Folder 1 (Box 4)
        - Folder 2 (Box 5)
    - Conference on Classroom Process, 1948; 1950 (Box 5)
    - Doyle, Charlotte Lackner, 1970 (Box 5)
      ("Authors' Letter" from McKeachie and Doyle)
    - Educational Testing Service, 1977-1985 (Box 5)
      (correspondence, guidelines)
    - Ford Fund, undated (Box 5)
      ("Report of the University of Michigan Project Under the Program of Grants for the Utilization of College Teaching Resources")
    - Goals of Life, undated, 1950 (Box 5)
      (correspondence, manuscript, "A Rating-Ranking Scale For Goals of Life")
    - Indiana University/Purdue University at Indianapolis, 1990 (Box 5)
      (re: external review of Department of Psychology)
    - Institute of Mental Measurements, 1976 (Box 5)
      (McKeachie reviews of various surveys)
    - Leslie College, 1964-1965 (Box 5)
      (re: experimental college)
    - McGill University, 1988 (Box 5)
      (review of Center for University Teaching and Learning)
    - Michigan State University, 1985 (Box 5)
      (re: student instructional rating system)
    - Minnesota, University of, 1988-1989 (Box 5)
      (re: series of lectures on teaching)
    - Mississippi-Doctoral-Level Psychology (report), 1978 (Box 5)
    - National Science Foundation, 1959-1960 (Box 5)
      (re: proposals to study undergraduate curriculum in psychology)
    - Oakland University, 1990 (Box 5)
      (report on visit to psychology department)
    - Oberlin College, 1972-1973 (Box 5)
      (re: visiting committee, includes final report)
    - Ohio State, 1987 (Box 5)
      (external review report)
    - Social Science Research Council, 1956-1977 (Box 5)
    - Teacher Training Internships, 1957 (Box 5)
    - University of Michigan
      - Athletics
        - General, 1975-1990 (Box 5)
        - Athletic Policy Committee, 1958-1960 (Box 5)
        - Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics, 1986-1987 (Box 5)
        - Committee to Study the Academic Performance of Athletes in the Literary College, 1957-1960 (Box 5)
        - Sports Service Building, 1971 (Box 5)
      - College of Human Services: Task Force on Curriculum and Assessment (report draft), 1974 (Box 5)
      - Committee on Undergraduate Studies, 1983 (Box 5)
      - Correspondence, 1976-1985 (Box 5)
      - Department of Psychology
        - Correspondence, 1961-1990 (Box 5)
        - Ratings, 1971 (Box 5)
      - Education and Psychology, 1976-1985 (Box 5)
      - English Composition Board, 1977-1981 (Box 5)
      - Faculty Senate, 1962-1963; 1971-1972 (Box 5)
      - Fleming, Robben, 1966 (Box 5)
      - Literature, Science, and the Arts, College of
        - Admissions Steering Committee, 1985 (Box 5)
        - Closed Circuit Television For College Instruction, undated (Box 5)
          (report by McKeachie)
        - Executive Committee, 1972-1984 (Box 5)
      - Mental Health Research Institute, 1967-1969 (Box 5)
      - Salary Policy, 1965-1976 (Box 5)
      - Teaching Assistants, undated, 1955; 1977 (Box 5)
      - Undergraduate Admissions Advisory Committee, 1989-1990; 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Vice President for Academic Affairs (1974) (Box 6)
    - University of Texas, undated (Box 6)
      (report on retreat with department of psychology)
    - Wabash College, 1973 (Box 6)
      (re: visiting committee and report on department of psychology)
- Center for Research on Learning and Teaching (CRLT)
  The Center for Research on Learning and Teaching subgroup includes correspondence files, speeches McKeachie gave reflecting his own research and the work of the Center, and topical files relating primarily to the administration of CRLT.
  - Correspondence
    The Correspondence series (1.5 linear feet) is comprised of two subseries, alphabetical and chronological. The correspondence is mostly outgoing from the 1970s, 1980s, and early 1990s, and there is duplication between the two subseries. The correspondence is primarily with other psychologists on topics related to McKeachie's affiliation with CRLT.
    - Alphabetical
      - A-U, 21 folders (Box 6)
      - V-Z, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Chronological
      - 1984 (Box 7)
      - 1985 (Box 7)
      - 1986 (Box 7)
      - 1987 (Box 7)
      - 1988 (Box 7)
      - 1989 (Box 7)
      - 1990 (Box 7)
      - 1991 (Box 7)
  - Course Materials
    The Course Materials (3 folders) series includes course objectives and some lecture outlines.
    - College Teaching (Psychology 863), 1964-1981 (Box 7)
    - Psychology in a Liberal Education (Psychology 309), 1949-1953 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 1949-1982 (Box 7)
  - Speeches
    The Speeches (.3 linear feet) are arranged by topic and within topic by title.
    - Education
      - Budget Cuts on the Quality of Education, 1981 (Box 7)
    - Faculty/Faculty Development
      - Advances in Faculty Development, 1979 (Box 7)
      - The Balancing Act: Teaching, Research, Life in General, 1982 (Box 7)
      - The Faculty As A Renewable Resource, 1983 (Box 7)
      - Student Ratings of Faculty, 1968; 1980 (Box 7)
      - Using Student Ratings: Lessons Learned, 1986 (Box 7)
    - Psychology
      - The New Look in Instructional Psychology, 1985 (Box 7)
      - Psychology and Adult Cognition, 1987 (Box 7)
      - Teaching Psychology of Today From a Developmental Point of View, 1979 (Box 7)
      - Teaching Psychology to Undergraduates, 1978 (Box 7)
    - Teaching
      - Applications of Cognitive Psychology to Teaching and Learning, 1985 (Box 7)
      - Can University Teaching Be Evaluated?, 1974 (Box 7)
      - Changing Teacher Behavior to Improve Instruction, 1974 (Box 7)
      - Cognition, Motivation, and College Teaching, 1986 (Box 7)
      - Contemporary Instructional Psychology and Educational Practice, 1985 (Box 7)
      - Education and Training of Educational Psychologists, 1984 (Box 7)
      - Effective Methods of Teaching and Lecturing, 1984 (Box 7)
      - Implications of Carnegie II for Education, 1979 (Box 7)
      - Improving Effectiveness, 1985 (Box 7)
      - Inferring Students' Cognitive Structure Using the "Ordered Tree" Technique, 1983 (Box 7)
      - Inspiring Students, 1988 (Box 7)
      - The Lecture, 1978 (Box 7)
      - Lecturing, Discussion Leading, Student Anxiety, and Learning to Learn, 1984 (Box 7)
      - Measuring Teaching Effectiveness, 1974-1976 (Box 7)
      - Motivating Students, Faculty, and Ourselves, 1987 (Box 7)
      - Peer Evaluation of University Teaching, 1985 (Box 8)
      - Resistance to Evaluation of Teaching, undated (Box 8)
      - Some Implications of Cognitive Psychology for College Teaching, 1979 (Box 8)
      - The State of the Art in Improving Learning and Teaching, 1977 (Box 8)
      - Student Anxieties and Learning Strategies, 1982 (Box 8)
      - The Teacher as an Adult Learner: The College Professor, 1981 (Box 8)
      - Teaching/Learning Improvement: The State of the Art, 1978 (Box 8)
      - Teaching Learning Strategies, 1985 (Box 8)
      - Teaching Thinking and Learning, 1987 (Box 8)
      - Teaching Values: Should We? Can We?, 1987 (Box 8)
      - What Works in Teaching?, 1981; circa 1982 (Box 8)
  - Topical
    The Topical series (.5 linear feet) is divided into two subseries: CRLT Administrative and Interuniversity. The CRLT files are from McKeachie's tenure as director of the center. Although quite incomplete in documenting his directorship, the Planning Meetings/Retreats, Research Grants Administered by CRLT, Review, and Staff Memos files contain valuable information on the activities of CRLT staff members and the budgetary difficulties the center encountered in the early 1980s.
    - CRLT Administrative
      - Annual Report -1976 (Box 8)
        (unbound)
      - Annual Salary Review, 1981-1983 (Box 8)
      - Budget, 1979-1982 (Box 8)
      - Correspondence, 1973-1978 (Box 8)
      - Deans, 1975-1983 (Box 8)
      - Department of Psychology, Five Year Review, 1980 (Box 8)
        (questionnaire filled out by McKeachie)
      - Directorship, 1975 (Box 8)
        (McKeachie letter re: what he would try to accomplish as CRLT director)
      - English Composition Board, 1981-1983 (Box 8)
      - Evaluations, 1972-1979 (Box 8)
        (of center and its programs)
      - Frye, Billy, 1979 (Box 8)
        (McKeachie letter assessing Frye's abilities as LSA dean)
      - Inteflex Program Evaluation, 1980 (Box 8)
      - Linguistics, 1980 (Box 8)
        (letter re: review of linguistics activity on campus)
      - Newsletter (correspondence), 1980-1982 (Box 8)
      - Objectives, 1976; 1979 (Box 8)
      - Personnel Review Committee, 1980-1981 (Box 8)
      - Planning Meetings/Retreats, 1974-1982 (Box 8)
      - Planning and Analysis, 1976-1977 (Box 8)
      - Primary Research Staff, 1976; 1981-1982 (Box 8)
      - Rackham Program to Promote International Partnerships, 1991 (Box 8)
      - Research Grants Administered by CRLT, 1978-1981 (Box 8)
      - Review, 1983 (Box 8)
        (includes copy of preliminary report and response by CRLT staff)
      - Staff Meetings (minutes), 1973; 1978 (Box 8)
      - Staff Memos, 1975-1983 (Box 8)
      - Staff Program Responsibilities, 1980 (Box 8)
      - Staff Service Activities, 1981 (Box 8)
      - Summer Institute, 1977-1978 (Box 8)
      - Teaching Assistant Training, 1979 (Box 8)
    - Interuniversity (Box 8)
      The Interuniversity subseries contains one folder documenting McKeachie's work with a panel studying faculty evaluation for the Committee on Institutional Cooperation.
      - Committee on Institutional Cooperation, Faculty Evaluation Panel, 1972-1978
- Sound recordings
  - Tapes of conference lectures and discussions (Box 9)
    (reel-to-reel stenorette tapes)
Related Material
For additional materials related to McKeachie's involvement with CRLT, see the records of the University of Michigan Center for Research on Learning and Teaching, which are available at the Bentley.